Saratoga Springs Open Space Project; Records apap155
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Saratoga Springs Open Space Project Records
1970-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap155
10.68 cubic ft.
The Saratoga Springs Open Space Project worked for the preservation of open space in Saratoga Springs. It supported the creation of nature trails, scenic walkways, and biking paths as well as vigorously opposed sprawl and loss of open space by organizing opposition to unsustainable development. In addition, the organization coordinated several programs aimed at aiding the development of Saratoga Springs and maintained a special interest in the development of the downtown area. The collection includes administrative files, grant files, material related to programs and issues, documentation of trails, and subject files.
Administrative History
The group that would become the Saratoga Springs Open Space Project (OSP) came together loosely in 1987. Its purpose was to help the city develop an open space supplement to the 1987 Saratoga Springs Master Plan. The OSP organized as an offshoot of the Saratoga Institute, a not-for-profit educational organization directed by Barbara Glaser. The OSP officially formed a board of directors in 1990. It produced the Open Space Plan, its vision for a "City in the Country" in 1991.
The Open Space Plan included 24 recommendations for the preservation of historic, natural, and rural spaces as wells as landmarks in the city of Saratoga Springs. It was widely distributed through presentations and open meetings. In 1993, the plan was revised and formally published through a grant provided by Rural New York's Environmental Action Fund. The Saratoga Springs City Council adopted the plan in 1994. The OSP continued to develop the plan and the Council unanimously accepted its updated form in 2002.
The Open Space Project continued to work for the preservation of open space in Saratoga Springs. The OSP supported the creation of nature trails, scenic walkways, and biking paths through programs like the ISTEA Rails to Trails program. Working with funds obtained through donations and grants, the OSP helped create the Bog Meadow Brook Nature Trail, Spring and Railroad Run Trails, Ramsdill Park, Ten Springs Woods Park, and a forty-seven mile looping recreational trail system throughout the city of Saratoga Springs.
The OSP has also vigorously opposed sprawl and loss of open space by organizing opposition to unsustainable development. One such campaign was the OSP's opposition to the construction of a truck bypass through the southern section of Saratoga Spa State Park. This opposition included the "Undiscovered Park" exhibit, an exhibition of art inspired by the State Park. Other campaigns include an opposition to a quarry near the Petrified Sea Gardens and protecting the rural character of the Exit 14 city entranceway against the development of an office park.
In addition, the OSP has helped coordinate several programs aimed at aiding the development of Saratoga Springs. The OSP maintained a special interest in the development of the downtown area, with projects like The Next Steps & Beyond forum and the Broadway Square mini-mall forum. These forums brought together people from all areas of Saratoga Springs to help generate ideas for the creative revitalization of the downtown.
Throughout its existence, Barbara Glaser has held executive positions in the OSP, starting as the temporary chairperson and continuing as co-chair of the advisory board. There has been a succession of fellow co-chairs, including Jeff Olsen, Douglas Ward, and Sally Hart Brown. The OSP maintained a small paid professional staff, including a Project Director and Newsletter Editor, and in 1998 hired Alain Ball Chinian as Executive Director. In 2003, the Saratoga Springs Open Space Project merged with the Land Trust of the Saratoga Region to form Saratoga PLAN (Preserving Land And Nature.) Thus the OSP no longer exists as a separate organization. Saratoga PLAN maintains a website at http://www.saratogaplan.org/.
There has been some confusion about the relations of the OSP to other organizations due to similar names and goals. The Saratoga Springs Open Space Project is not connected to the Open Space Institute, a statewide organization that also seeks to preserve scenic and natural landscape. However, the OSP has received grant funding from the Open Space Institute for trail building. The Saratoga Institute is a non-profit educational institute founded in 1985, in Saratoga Springs. It works through projects, like the OSP, the Humor Project, and The Association for the Cooperative Advancement of Science and Education. It is not related to the Sagamore Institute or the Human Resource Analysis organization also called the Saratoga Institute.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to the activities and interests of the Saratoga Springs Open Space Project. The records trace its existence from 1991, when it began to be a functioning non-profit organization, until 2002. Materials from before 1991 are generally articles or news clippings. These materials were primarily retained and maintained by Barbara Glaser, one of the founding members and co-chair of the Advisory Board throughout most of the OSP's existence. The records include meeting minutes, correspondence, grant applications, position statements, publications, news clippings, and articles.
These materials do not contain anything from the OSP's formative years spent creating the Open Space Plan, nor do they contain anything relating to its merger with the Land Trust of the Saratoga Region into the Saratoga PLAN organization. There is also no information relating to the Saratoga Institute or its other projects.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information on the environmental issues of concern to the Saratoga Springs Open Space Project. For a complete list of related collections see the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment. Of particular interest are the records of Environmental Clearinghouse, Inc. (APAP-180), a non-profit organization that has worked with Saratoga PLAN.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1991-2002, undated
Series 2: Grant Files, 1991-1998, undated
Series 3: Programs and Issues, 1970-1972, 1981-1986, 1989-2002
Series 4: Trails, 1986-2000, undated
Series 5: Subject Files, 1973-1976, 1980-1982, 1987-2003, undated
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Barbara Glaser and the Saratoga Institute in September 2004.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Conservation and the Environment; Bicycle trails--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Nature trails--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Land use--New York (State)--Saratoga County--Planning; City planning--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Social ecology--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Environmental management--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Highway planning--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Parks--New York (State)--Saratoga County; Clippings; Correspondence; Memorandum; Minutes; Grant proposals; Reports; Saratoga Springs Open Space Project
- Administrative Files, 1991-2002; Undated; 1; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of meeting minutes, agendas and notes as well as publications, articles, news clippings, and memoranda all directly pertaining to the operation of the Saratoga Springs Open Space Project (OSP). The publications include issues of Common Ground, the OSP newsletter, from 1992-1997, with scattered issues thereafter until 2001. Also included are meeting minutes and agendas from 1993-1999.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Budget Reports, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Common Ground Newsletter, 1992-2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - History of the Open Space Project, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Lobbying by Charitable Organizations, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Meeting Agendas, Minutes, 1993-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Meeting Agendas, Minutes, 1997-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Membership Correspondence, 1994-1995; 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Open Space Plan, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Open Space Plan, 2002 Update, PowerPoint Slides (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Open Space Project, Pamphlets, Bumper Sticker, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Open Space Project Board, Photographs, Negatives, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Open Space Project History, News Clippings, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Open Space Project Long Range Planning, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Open Space Project Position Papers, 1991; 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Processes for Board Development, Memorandum, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
- Grant Files, 1991-1998; Undated; 2; 1 cubic foot
  The documents in this series relate to the OSP's attempts to obtain grant funding. It contains grant applications, requests for proposals, correspondence and publications. Grants were sought from organizations such as the Land Trust Alliance, Open Space Institute, and the New York State Council on the Arts. Government funding for trail building was applied for under the Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act (ISTEA.) Applications submitted to the same organization are divided by the application year.
  - American Greenways Du Pont Awards Program, 1993-1996; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 1)
  - CB North America, Grant Proposal, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 2)
  - Community Forestry Program, Request for Proposals, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 3)
  - Community Foundation, Application Guidelines, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 4)
  - Community Foundation, Newsletter, Annual Report, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 5)
  - Corporate Grants for Bikeway Proposal, Correspondence, Marling Lists, News Clippings, 1995; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 6)
  - Environmental Grants Program, Federal Register, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 7)
  - Environmental Grants, 1993; 1996-1997; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 8)
  - Environmental Protection Agency Title 9, Correspondence, Publications, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 9)
  - Fleet Bank, Bikeway Proposal, Grant Application, Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 10)
  - Grants, Press Releases, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 11)
  - Intermodal Surface Transport Efficiency Act, Correspondence, New York State Department of Transportation Regional Director, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 12)
  - Intermodal Surface Transport Efficiency Act, Grant Application, Handbook, Pamphlets, 1993; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 13)
  - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act, New York State Trails Council, Meeting Minutes, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 14)
  - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act, Press Release, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 15)
  - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act, Project Development Handbook, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 16)
  - Land Trust Alliance, Grant Application, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 17)
  - Letters of Support, A.C. Drake, Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 18)
  - The Minneapolis Foundation, Guidelines for Grant Applications, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 19)
  - Municipal Canal Development Program, Request for Proposals, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 20)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, Application Guidelines, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 21)
  - National Recreational Trails Fund Act, Grant Application, Correspondence Publication, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 22)
  - Newsletters, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 23)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1991 Application, 1991-1993 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 24)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1991-1992 Application, Grant Application, Application Instructions (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 25)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1992-1993 Application (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 26)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1993-1994 Application, Grant Application (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 27)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1994-1995 Application, Application Appendices (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 28)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1994-1995 Application, Funding for "Envision Saratoga" Exhibit, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 29)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1995-1996 Application, 1998-1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 30)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1996-1997 Application, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 31)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1997-1998 Application, Correspondence, Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 32)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, Guidelines, Publications, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 33)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, Institutional Development, Meeting Minutes, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 34)
  - New York State Nonpoint Source Implementation Grants Program, Request for Proposals, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 35)
  - Open Space Institute, 1993 Application, Grant Application, Correspondence, Annual Report (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 36)
  - Open Space Institute, 1994 Application, Grant Application, Correspondence (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 37)
  - Open Space Institute, 1995 Application, Grant Application (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 38)
  - Open Space Institute, 1995 Application, Letters of Acceptance, Correspondence (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 39)
  - Open Space Institute, 1996 Application (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 40)
  - Requests for Proposals, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 41)
  - Rotary Club, Bikeway Proposal, Correspondence, Grant Application, News Clippings, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 42)
  - Rural New York Grants Program, Pamphlets, Correspondence, Press Releases, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 43)
  - Soroptimist International of Saratoga County, Bikeway Proposal, Grant Application, Correspondence, 1995; Undated (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 44)
  - Soroptimist International of Saratoga County, Grant Application, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 45)
  - Soroptimist International of Saratoga County, Grant Application, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 46)
  - Special Assessment District, Bikeway Proposal, Grant Application, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 47)
  - Turner Foundation, Grant Application, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Grant Files), Folder 48)
- Programs and Issues, 1970-1972; 1981-1986; 1989-2002; 3; 4.36 cubic ft.
  This series is a subject file of materials related to the activities and interests of the OSP. Particularly well represented are some of the conflicts over proposed development, such as the building of a truck bypass and the High Rock golf course in Saratoga Spa State Park. Also included are materials from The Next Steps & Beyond forum and the mini-mall committee, which dealt with ways to develop the downtown Saratoga Springs area. Other issues include the move of the Saratoga Farmer's Market to High Rock Spring Park, the construction of the Saratoga National Golf Club and the Vote Yes! organization, a side project advocating the passage of a 2002 bond referendum to pay for the 2001 Environmental Parks and Open Area Protection Program. Extensive news clipping files are filed separately at the end of the series.
  - Adams Road, Scenic Bypass Designation, Correspondence, Legislation, 1992; 1997-1998 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 1)
  - Anderson Property, Notes, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 2)
  - Arrowhead Road Archeology/Recreation Site, Survey Map, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 3)
  - Big Box Development, News Clippings, 1995; 1997 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, Address Lists, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 5)
  - Budget Surplus, News Clippings, 2000 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 6)
  - Bulk Petroleum Storage, Department of Environmental Conservation Publications, 1985-1992 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 7)
  - Championing New York's Parks Conference, Conference Materials, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 8)
  - Community Land Preservation Referendum, 2001 Bond Act, 2001-2002; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 9)
  - Community Land Preservation Referendum, Environmental, Parks and Open Areas' Protection Program, 2001 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 10)
  - Community Land Preservation Referendum, Letters to the Editor, Drafts, 2002 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 11)
  - Community Land Preservation Referendum, News Clippings, 2001 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 12)
  - Community Land Preservation Referendum, Vote Yes! Organization, 2002 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 13)
  - Comprehension Plan, Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 14)
  - Comprehensive Plan for the City of Saratoga Springs, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 15)
  - "Conserving Open Space in New York State, A Summary of the Plan", Department of Environmental Conservation, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Molly Brinelle, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 17)
  - Department of Transportation Regulations, Memorandum, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 18)
  - Downtown Business Association Public Meetings, Agenda, Notes, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 19)
  - Earth Day 1993, Ann Grey Gallery, Planning Summary, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 20)
  - Endangered/Threatened Species in City of Saratoga Springs, New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, 2002 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 21)
  - Environmental Planning Lobby, Mailing List, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 22)
  - Evolution Matrix, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 23)
  - Excelsior Avenue, News Clippings, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 24)
  - Exit 14, News Clippings, 1994 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 25)
  - Farm Properties, Lot Statistics, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 26)
  - Farmer's Market, Archeological Survey, Correspondence, Reports, Presentation Materials, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 27)
  - Farmer's Market, Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Minutes, Notes, 1983; 1986; 1996; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 28)
  - Farmer's Market, High Rock Park, Grant Agreements, 1981; 1986 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 29)
  - Friends of the Saratoga Spa State Park, By-laws, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 30)
  - "Funding Land Resource, Acquisition, Recreation Facility Development and Stewardship in New York State", Charles Morrison, Study, 1989 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 31)
  - Grand Avenue, Rezoning Notes, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 32)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Articles, Newsletters, News Clippings, 1994-1995; 1997; 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 33)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Correspondence, Audubon Society of the Capital Region, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 34)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Correspondence, Memoranda, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 35)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 36)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 37)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Correspondence, Memoranda, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 38)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Environmentally Sound Golf Course Development, Publications, 1992; 1999 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 39)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Integrated Post Management, Correspondence, Reports, 1992; 1996; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 40)
  - High Rock Golf Course, New York Coalition for Alternatives to Pesticides, Articles, Leaflets, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 41)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Position Statement, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 42)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Scoping for Draft Environmental Impact Statement, Correspondence, Final Scope, Maps, Summary, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 43)
  - High Rock Golf Course, SEQR Assessment Form, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 44)
  - High Rock Golf Course, Toxic Chemicals, Articles, 1989; 1991-1994 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 45)
  - Housing Units Along Alternate Routes, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 46)
  - Kaufman Controversy, Correspondence, News Clippings, Program, 1994; 1996; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 47)
  - Land Planners, Appraisers and Consultants, Qualifications of Ronald Mechur, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 48)
  - Letter Writing Campaign, Instructions, News Clippings, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 49)
  - Local Open Space planning Handbook, Outline, 1993 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 50)
  - Loughberry Lake, 1972; 1994; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 51)
  - Mini Mall, Diagrams, Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 52)
  - Mini Mall, News Clippings, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 53)
  - Mini Mall, Mini Mall/Broadway Square Ad Hoc Committee, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 54)
  - "New York State Parkland: Held in the Public Trust Should Require Legislative for Alienation or Conversion", Emily Muller, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 55)
  - The Next Steps and Beyond, Community Forum on the Future of Downtown, Forum Responses, 1994 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 56)
  - The Next Step and Beyond, Fliers and Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 57)
  - The Next Step and Beyond, News Clippings, 1992-1993; 1995 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 58)
  - Old Schuylerville Road, Rezoning, Position Statement, Maps, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 59)
  - "Preserve and Protect: Challenges Facing New York's State Park System", Nelson Rockefeller Institute of Government, 1993 (Box 1 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 60)
  - Saratoga County Water Quality Committee, Meeting Agendas, Minutes, 1994-1998 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 1)
  - Saratoga National Golf Club, 1997-2001 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 2)
  - Saratoga National Golf Club, Maps, 1995; Undated (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 3)
  - Saratoga Spa State Park, Concessionaire Request for Proposals, 1997 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 4)
  - Saratoga Spa State Park, Development Plan, Correspondence, Maps, News Clippings, 1995; Undated (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 5)
  - Saratoga Spa State Park, Great Blue Heron Rookery, Report, 1996 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 6)
  - Saratoga Spa State Park, Maps, 1967; 1995 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 7)
  - Saratoga Spa State Park, News Clippings, 1997-1998 (Box 2 (3-Programs and Issues), Folder 8)